On the 22nd of July 1943, the US 7th Army captured
Palermo, the largest city on Sicily, after General
George Patton’s forces had taken 100 miles of Axis
territory in 72 hours. Patton was relentless and
continued charging about Sicily, conquering towns
and capturing tens of thousands of prisoners of
war. In response, three days after the fall of
Palermo, the Grand Council of Fascism removed
Benito Mussolini from power. After Sicily, Patton
was the most feared Allied commander in Europe.
So why was this tactically brilliant general
sidelined when the D-Day campaign took place
a year later? This is the story of George Patton,
a brilliant general and utterly flawed man.
The man known to history as George Smith Patton
Jnr. was born on the 11th of November 1885, in
San Gabriel in the state of California. Although
he was generally known as George Jnr., he was
theoretically George Patton III, as his father and
grandfather both had the same name as him.
His father, George, was an attorney, businessman
and politician who served for three months as the
District Attorney of Los Angeles County in 1887
and much later as the Mayor of San Marino. The
family had a military background and young
George’s grandfather had died fighting for
the Confederacy during the American Civil War.
George Jnr.’s mother was Ruth Wilson, the daughter
of one of California’s wealthiest men, Benjamin
Davis Wilson, a businessman who had moved out to
California when it was still under Mexican rule
and who subsequently became the second Mayor of
Los Angeles in the middle of the gold rush after
the region was annexed by the US in 1848. After
Ruth married George Patton Snr. they lived in San
Gabriel on the Lake Vineyard estate owned by her
father. They had two children, George Jnr., and
his younger sister Anne, who was known as Nita.
The Patton family were descended from the Lords
of Glamorgan, a Welsh family, as well as from King
Edward I of England, while they had Scottish and
French Huguenot ancestry and were tied to a branch
of the family of George Washington.
George Jnr. was tutored at home until he was
eleven years old. His literacy skills were
consequently under-developed when he began
attending Stephen Clark’s School for boys, a
private school in Pasadena. Once he did learn
to read, he did so avidly and became especially
interested in books on military history and
commanders such as Julius Caesar, the Carthaginian
general Hannibal and Napoleon Bonaparte.
He also read the works of John Singleton Mosby,
a Confederate cavalry commander known as the
“Gray Ghost” on account of his ability to
attack the enemy and then seemingly vanish.
The Pattons’ own extended legacy as a military
family, with many relatives who fought in the
American Revolutionary War and the Civil War,
left an impression on George from a young age
and became an important part of his identity.
It was unsurprising, then, that at seventeen
years of age George set off across the country to
enrol in the Virginia Military Institute in 1903,
an institution which both his father and
grandfather had attended before him. He was later
nominated to the military academy at West Point.
This was already established as the elite training
school for future military officers in the US.
Alumni included Ulysses S. Grant, George Custer,
“Stonewall” Jackson and John Pershing, the latter
of whom would soon play a role in Patton’s career.
In some ways Patton was well suited to life at
West Point, but he struggled at mathematics,
a subject that was considered increasingly
important at the academy in a time when
military logistics were becoming central
to military command. He excelled at sports,
as he was already an accomplished horseman and
competed in track and field events too. He joined
the football team but after injuring his arm
he moved over to the fencing team instead.
After his initial difficulties, George did well
at West Point and was made a cadet sergeant major
in his junior year and an adjutant in his senior
year. After graduating, he left in June 1909 after
being commissioned as a second lieutenant assigned
to the 15th Cavalry Division at Fort Sheridan in
Illinois. Later he was transferred to Fort Myer in
Virginia. On the 26th of May 1910, Patton married
Beatrice Banning Ayer, the daughter of a Boston
industrialist, Frederick Ayer, at Beverly Farms in
Massachusetts. They went on to have three children
together, Beatrice, Ruth and George Patton IV.
While still serving at Fort Myer as quartermaster
of his troop in 1911, George befriended Henry
Stimson, the Secretary of War, whose aide he
became. George also continued as a fencer and his
skill led to him being sent to the participate
at the Summer Olympics in Stockholm in 1912,
where he finished in 5th place overall in the
modern pentathlon, which consisted of swimming,
pistol shooting, running, fencing and riding.
Patton was the highest placed of the non-Swedish
participants. He was among the top five performers
in fencing, swimming and horse-riding, but he
placed in 20th in the shooting event. Controversy
arose over the scoring for George’s shooting,
as he had used a .38 caliber pistol, whilst
other competitors were using .22 calibre pistols.
George argued that some of his shots must have
passed straight through the previous holes he
had made in the score card because of the larger
impact holes that the higher calibre pistol had
made. The adjudicators disagreed and concluded
that some of his shots had missed the target
completely. If his argument was correct, he
would likely have medalled at the Olympics.
He returned home via France, where he
studied fencing under Sir Charles Cléry,
a Master at Arms of the French Cavalry Academy. On
his return to the US, Patton designed a new sword,
the Model 1913 Cavalry Saber, known as the ‘Patton
Saber’. In 1913, an order was placed by the
military for 20,000 of these blades. Later he was
made ‘Master of the Sword’, the most prestigious
title offered to swordsmanship instructors at Fort
Riley in Kansas, where he was then stationed.
Patton attended the Mounted Service School after
returning to the US and graduated in the summer
of 1915. He was assigned to the 15th Cavalry,
which was bound for the Philippines, an American
colony at the time, but before he was sent to
Southeast Asia he persuaded influential contacts
in Washington to intervene to have him re-assigned
to the 8th Cavalry instead at Fort Bliss in Texas,
as he feared a post in the Philippines would prove
to be a career dead-end. Instead, with the Mexican
Revolution underway throughout the 1910s, and
the war threatening to spill over the border into
places like Texas, Patton viewed assignment to
Fort Bliss as preferential over the Philippines.
In this way, Patton’s first experience of active
military combat came in 1916 when he took part
in the Pancho Villa Expedition, the US army’s
campaign against the paramilitary forces of
Mexican revolutionary Francisco ‘Pancho’
Villa, whose men had attacked the border
town of Columbus in New Mexico on the 9th of March
1916, along with nearby Camp Furlong. In response,
General Frederick Funston, leader of the 8th
Cavalry, who was stationed at Fort Bliss, was
ordered to secure the Mexico-United States border
and to pursue Villa and his men. Patton’s unit was
not part of the force, and so George appealed to
commander John Pershing to serve as his personal
aide in the campaign, acting as a courier and
helping to plan the action along the border area.
George’s eagerness and dedication to the task
at hand impressed Pershing and in April 1916
he appointed Patton to command troop C of the
13th Cavalry, the unit that was tasked with
hunting down Villa and his subordinates. Thus,
on the 14th of May 1916 Patton first saw combat,
a date also famous today for the first use
of motorised transport in American military
history as cavalry units began to diversify away
from horses. However, the overall expedition,
which ended in February 1917, was ultimately
unsuccessful, as they failed in their main goal,
which was to capture ‘Pancho’ Villa,
instead killing several of his followers,
including Colonel Candelario Cervantes, General
Francisco Beltran and Villa’s second in command,
Julio Cardenas. At one point during his mission
Patton and his subordinates, in a trio of Dodge
touring cars, encountered a number of Villa’s men,
who were foraging for food. According to accounts,
Patton shot three of the bandits. Patton’s brash
approach to military command, where he had no
reservations about putting himself in harm’s
way, gained him both admiration and notoriety.
The American press labelled him as the
‘bandit-killer’ shortly afterwards.
Patton was promoted to the rank of first
lieutenant after this excursion after Villa.
For several months Pershing, Patton and their men
remained on the Mexico border conducting training.
However, even though the civil war dragged on
in Mexico, the focus of US military activity was
soon drawn elsewhere to Europe after the US entry
into the First World War in April 1917. Pershing,
with Patton in tow, was appointed to command the
advance American Expeditionary Force that was sent
to Western Europe while wider war mobilisation was
underway at home. Patton personally requested to
join Pershing in France and his request was
granted, resulting in him being promoted to
Captain, after which he joined Pershing in the
advance party of officers that headed to Europe.
There he worked as Pershing’s personal aide,
overseeing the last minute training of American
troops, who were steadily arriving in their tens
of thousands. After overseeing this work in Paris,
in September 1917 Patton was reassigned to
Chaumont as post adjutant, being placed in
charge of the company that ran the American base.
Patton was not temperamentally suited to this
position and he complained to Pershing, asking
him to reassign him to front line duties.
It was during this period that Patton first
encountered the piece of military hardware
that would revolutionise both his own strategic
thinking and the entire nature of modern warfare.
The first tanks were developed and deployed
in 1916 by the British as a pioneering means
of reducing the lethality of machine guns on
the Western Front. By placing men inside what
was basically a giant, moving metal box, it was
envisaged that the stalemate created by trench
warfare could be broken. Soon the Germans, and in
particular the French, were developing what would
come to be described as armoured cavalry. After a
bout of sick leave as he recovered from jaundice,
Patton made the acquaintance of Colonel Fox
Connor, an operations officer with the American
Expeditionary Force in Paris, who encouraged
Patton to seek a position commanding one of the
new tank regiments. Consequently, on the 10th
of November 1917, Patton was assigned to the
American Expeditionary Force Light Tank School.
While he was fascinated with the possibilities
that the new machines offered, he had to acquaint
himself with the nuances of the hardware. He was
therefore attached to the French Tank School
where he first drove a Renault FT light tank.
After doing so, he became convinced that these
new weapons were the future of terrestrial combat.
Once he heard that the British were planning
a mass attack of tanks, on the German line at
Cambrai, which proved to be the largest use of
these vehicles thus far, Patton arranged to meet
Colonel J. F. C. Fuller, the Chief of Staff
of the British Tank Corps, in order to learn
more about how to incorporate the metallic
weapons of war into the US armed forces.
On his way back to Paris after meeting with
Fuller not far from Cambrai, Patton stopped at
the Renault factory to watch tanks being assembled
there. He was promoted to the rank of Major in
January of 1918. Less than a month later, the
Americans were given ten tanks by the French to
use at their training school at Bourg. As the only
relatively senior American officer to have driven
one of these, Patton was assigned to instruct
others in how to use these armoured vehicles.
At the same time, he was trying to convince
his superiors within the American military that
the use of the tanks on the battlefield was the
future. This was easier said than done, as at this
early stage in their development, these were still
extremely slow and often mechanically unreliable.
Many within the American Expeditionary Force
believed they had limited utility. Undaunted,
Patton tenaciously continued to press his case,
and it wasn’t long before tanks were beginning to
be incorporated into the American army’s battle
plans for the closing stages of the conflict.
In tandem, Patton was promoted once again, in
April 1918, to the rank of Lieutenant Colonel.
He took part on the 12th of September 1918 during
the Saint-Mihiel offensive and again on the 26th
of the month in the Meuse-Argonne offensive,
where he was injured whilst storming the German
lines after his tanks had become isolated and cut
off from the main attack. Though the bullet wound
in his left leg was serious, Patton commanded the
attack from the safety of a shell-hole for over an
hour before being rescued, insisting on personally
submitting his report of the battle to the command
post before going to the field hospital where
he was treated for the injury. The wound kept
Patton out of the fighting until the war ended
on the 11th of November 1918. Despite not having
experienced much direct combat in the Great War,
Patton had helped to demonstrate to the American
forces the potential power of tank warfare and
that he was a commander with innovative ideas.
The inter-war years were not a particularly happy
time for Patton, as he became agitated by the
extended peace and the lack of opportunities for
an active command. In the interim he continued
to push for the expanded incorporation of tank
divisions into the military. In 1919 he was sent
to Washington D.C. to join a committee dedicated
to writing a manual on tank operations for future
conflicts. At this juncture he began arguing that
tanks should have their own armoured unit, rather
than fulfilling the role of simply supporting
infantry divisions. Yet, while his push for the
development of independent armoured divisions was
supported by his friend, Dwight D. Eisenhower, and
the Secretary of War, Dwight Davis, there was no
appetite in Washington for funding such a costly
initiative now that the war was over. As a result,
the first armoured corps within the US army would
not be developed until 1940. Patton moved between
various posts in the years that followed. In 1924,
he attended the General staff college, where
he graduated 25th out of a school of 248.
In the summer of 1932, in the midst of the
economic crisis of the Great Depression,
over 17,000 World War One veterans converged
on the capital in protest over the failure
of the government to convert their wartime
bonuses into cash. On the 28th of July 1932,
this protest turned violent when the police
attempted to break up the demonstration.
Patton was ordered to march with 600 men against
the protestors however he was reluctant to do so,
having considerable sympathy for the veterans’
cause. Nevertheless, he obeyed orders and the
so-called ‘Bonus Army’ was driven away. At the
start of 1935 Patton was transferred to Hawaii.
While he was there, he observed the growing
expansion of the Japanese Empire in the Far
East and the large Japanese community on the
Hawaiian islands. He therefore developed a plan
to detain the Japanese people living in Hawaii in
the event of an invasion. This was controversial,
though it ultimately became government policy
after the Japanese attack on Pearl Harbor in
December 1941. In 1937, as the Japanese invaded
China, Patton also correctly predicted a potential
surprise attack on the American Pacific
Fleet by the Japanese in future years,
in a paper he wrote entitled ‘Surprise’.
As the peacetime lull continued and Patton
became bored he developed a drinking problem
and even began an extra-marital affair with his
niece-in-law, Jean Gordon, when he was 49 and
she was 21, although there is a debate among
historians as to whether or not this affair
really took place. Some biographies argue it
was merely a rumour without any evidence to
support it. The end of his long hiatus from
active war came nearer on the 1st of September
1939, when Nazi Germany invaded Poland and the
Second World War began in Europe. Although the
US was not initially involved in the conflict,
it began to mobilise as a precaution and Patton
worked to ensure that this mobilisation included
the building up of independent armoured divisions.
In 1940 the 1st and 2nd armoured divisions were
created. On the 4th of April 1941 Patton was
promoted to the rank of Major-General. Patton
also staged a practice exercise in which 1,000
tanks and armoured vehicles raced from the state
of Georgia to Florida. To increase his tactical
knowledge, Patton earned a pilot’s license,
so that he could observe these exercises from
the sky and thus gain a better insight into the
movements of armoured units across long distances.
These huge exercises in the southeast of the
country gained considerable attention, captivating
the nation with Patton’s new method of warfare.
Patton also developed a training centre in the
deserts of California in 1941, aiming to simulate
the conditions of the North African Desert, which
had developed into an Allied theatre of war.
On the 7th of December 1941, just as Patton
had predicted four years earlier, the Japanese
launched a devastating surprise assault on the
American naval base at Pearl Harbour in Hawaii.
The US declared war on Japan the following day
and on Japan’s ally, Germany, three days later,
forming the Allied Alliance with Britain,
the Soviet Union and other powers like Canada
and the Free French. On the 15th of January
1942, Patton was placed in command of the 1st
armoured corps and immediately began stepping up
training exercises in the desert training centre.
Patton’s speed and aggression defined his command
style and his military career as a whole. In this
sense he was very similar to the Axis General,
Erwin Rommel, who had dominated the German command
in the North African theatre. Perhaps it was not
surprising then that Patton’s first major command
in the Second World War was in North Africa, where
his friend, Lieutenant General Dwight Eisenhower,
assigned Patton to help plan the US invasion
of North Africa, known as Operation Torch.
This was intended to support the British forces
already stationed in Egypt and to push out the
Germans and Italians while also subduing the Vichy
French forces in Algeria and Morocco. Patton was
given command of the western taskforce, some
33,000 men, who he ordered to begin landings
centred on Casablanca in Morocco on the 8th
of November 1942. Before these landings began,
Patton addressed his troops in a way which
epitomised his military philosophy, stating,
“We shall attack and attack, until we are
exhausted, and then we shall attack again.”
Despite meeting staunch resistance from the Vichy
French forces, Patton’s men gained a beachhead in
Morocco and pressed on to Casablanca, which
fell on the 11th of November. Patton then
turned this into a military port which acted
as an entry-point henceforth for further Allied
supplies and reinforcements for the North Africa
campaign. A conference of the Allied leaders,
US President Franklin Delano Roosevelt and British
Prime Minister Winston Churchill, was held here
in January 1943. However, US forces suffered a
setback weeks later when the 2nd Corps under Major
General Frendendall was defeated at the Kasserine
Pass in Tunisia by Field Marshal Rommel’s Afrika
Korps. The poorly led American troops were pushed
back 50 miles by Rommel’s experienced veterans,
taking heavy casualties along the way. Patton
responded by removing Frendendall from command,
heightening military discipline across US forces,
pushing his troops hard, and instilling fear and
discipline into the men. In response the men
nicknamed Patton ‘Old Blood and Guts’ due to
his lust for battle and harsh command-style.
Nonetheless, Patton was an inspiring figure
for his troops, setting an example for them
with his theatrical image, wearing a highly
polished helmet with cavalry boots and brandishing
a pair of ivory-handled pistols, a flashy bit of
behaviour he had adopted all the way back in 1916
after he acquired one of these guns in New Mexico.
He also travelled in a vehicle bearing his rank
insignia in large letters with sirens blaring from
the truck to indicate he was unafraid of enemy
snipers. Patton’s measures helped US forces to
swiftly regain the offensive, and on the 17th
of March 1943 they captured the Tunisian city
of Gafsa in the battle of El Guettar.
With the situation in Tunisia improving for the
Allies, Eisenhower recalled Patton in April to
take control of American forces for Operation
Husky, the planned Allied invasion of Sicily
to open a Southern Front in Europe. This was
scheduled for July 1943, however Patton was
frustrated as the British commanders clearly
viewed the Americans as inexperienced and
tried to side-line his 7th Army in favour
of British General Bernard Montgomery leading
the expedition. Patton soon proved them wrong.
After the Allies landed in Sicily on the 10th of
July, Montgomery’s forces met strong resistance,
in response to which Patton charged onwards
with his men and captured the Sicilian capital,
Palermo. Then, with Montgomery’s advance slowed
by strong Axis resistance, Patton led his forces
deeper into Sicily and reached the northeastern
port of Messina on the 17th of August. With this
advance, Patton’s armoured forces had thus
achieved a lightning quick success in Sicily,
inflicting over 110,000 casualties on the Italians
and Germans, mostly in captured prisoners of
war. Patton had distinguished himself in this
campaign as one of the finest Allied commanders,
but his fierce temper threatened to undermine his
military success. Unlike many other commanders,
George Patton made frequent visits to combat
hospitals, seeing it as, a general’s duty to view
his wounded troops. On the 3rd of August Patton
came across an infantryman in a hospital with no
visible injuries. After questioning him, Patton
erupted and slapped the soldier, pushing him out
of the hospital tent. A week later he repeated
this behaviour with another soldier and accused
him of cowardice. Eisenhower reprimanded Patton
for these incidents and attempted to prevent
the story being released to the American public.
However, it was leaked in November 1943, causing a
furious reaction from Congress and the public, and
greatly denting Patton’s domestic reputation.
Patton’s behaviour had raised enough questions
about his temperament that his subordinate,
Omar Bradley, was seen thereafter as being more
reliable and was chosen to lead the US 1st Army
in the upcoming invasion of Nazi-occupied France.
This does not mean that Patton’s services were
not availed of. The Allied command knew that the
Germans respected and feared Patton more than any
other Allied commander. Thus, Patton was placed
in charge of a fictitious US army group, as part
of the Allied plan was to deceive the Germans
as to where and when they would invade France.
This was the 1st US Army Group or FUSAG, and
the leaked intelligence on the positioning
and communications of the fake army convinced
Berlin that the Allied landing would occur at
Pas-de-Calais, when in reality, the chosen
Allied landing spot was further west on the
beaches of Normandy. Once the decoy attempt had
been undertaken, Patton was redeployed and given
command of a real force in France, the US 3rd
Army. He arrived to France on the 6th July 1944,
a month after the initial D-Day landings. Patton’s
mission was to take his force west to capture
the ports of Brittany. On the 1st of August
1944, with his armoured units leading the way,
Patton stormed through the northwestern corner of
France at breakneck speed, quickly overrunning the
province. The speed with which he carried out this
exercise indicated that Patton knew that Brittany
was only a sideshow in the war. He wanted to get
back into the thick of the action in trying to
liberate Paris and then pushing on into Belgium
and eastern France. Thus, with Brittany subdued,
Patton reoriented his forces eastwards and on
the 3rd of August began his lightning advance.
When battling through the German defences
at Normandy in June, advancing a mile a day
was considered good progress for the Allies.
However, Patton demanded that his fast-moving
armoured divisions advance upwards of 50
miles a day. In this way he was soon able
to turn back eastwards from Brittany and he
and his 3rd Army played an important role in
the trapping of tens of thousands of German
soldiers in the Falaise pocket in mid-August.
Patton was greatly assisted by air support during
his French campaign, whose reconnaissance patrols,
informed Patton’s forces of enemy positions, and
whose bombers provided protection and support for
his armoured columns. Additionally, air support
was incredibly valuable for Patton in securing his
flanks, as during his lightning advances, Patton’s
lines often became long and thin, making the rear
of his forces vulnerable to enemy counterattacks.
With the Battle of Normandy virtually over after
the capture of the Falaise pocket, Patton wished
to advance on Paris, but he was directed to move
southeast towards Lorraine in eastern France,
thus allowing the Free French forces to liberate
their own capital on the 25th of August 1944.
Patton’s eastwards offensive came to a halt at
the end of August as supplies, in particular
fuel, began to dwindle. He was extremely
frustrated by this and criticised Montgomery
and other Allied commanders, claiming he was
being hampered by the slow movement of others.
The autumn of 1944 was frustrating for Patton. His
forces were battered by heavy rain and met
stern resistance from the Germans, who had
been preparing the border defences between France
and Germany since D-Day. There was, for instance,
staunch resistance met in the city of Metz,
which didn’t fall until the 22nd of November.
Ever the military history buff, Patton commented
to his staff upon the fall of Metz that it was the
first time in over 400 years, that the city, so
often a battleground in Europe’s violent history,
had been taken by direct assault. There was
a touch of hyperbole here. The city had been
captured by the Germans in 1870 during the
early stages of the Franco-Prussian War,
though that was after a two-month long siege. By
early December 1944, Patton’s supply situation was
improving, as the capture of the port of Antwerp
by the Allies in September 1944 had allowed for
increased supply from Britain to the continent.
He consequently became central to the planning for
launching a winter offensive aimed at Frankfurt
and the River Rhine. However, in mid-December the
Nazis launched a desperate counterattack through
the Ardennes forest with the goal of retaking
Antwerp and slowing the Allies advance into
Germany. Remarkably, Patton and his staff officers
were the only major Allied command unit to see
that the Germans were preparing to counterattack
in advance of the assault with quarter of a
million men on the 16th of December 1944. Due to
his prior intelligence of the assault, Patton was
already planning an attack on the southern flank
of the bulge that the German advance created
in the Allied lines through their offensive.
He thus informed Eisenhower, that he could engage
the German flank and Patton’s troops duly turned
north to smash into the flanks of the advancing
Axis army. Patton’s 3rd Army pushed on in the days
that followed to the Belgian town of Bastogne,
which they reached on the 26th of December. There,
the US 101st Airborne Division had been surrounded
by the Germans. Patton’s move opened up a supply
corridor for the besieged Allied forces at
Bastogne. Patton’s incredible manoeuvre,
diverting two-thirds of his army from the
front line and racing to the German flank
within two days, helped the Allies quickly turn
the tide of the Battle of the Bulge, preventing
the Germans from reaching the River Meuse. His
rapid and decisive manoeuvres in response to the
assault contrasted with the slow response and
lack of foresight of the other US generals.
Patton was the only Allied commander, who came
out of the Ardennes Offensive, with his reputation
enhanced. He was consequently given greater
resources in the spring offensive into Germany.
Patton’s Palatinate offensive began on the 12th
of March 1945. During it, his aggressiveness
allowed him to exploit the weakened Wehrmacht,
pushing his armoured divisions in between gaps in
the German lines. The 3rd Army made spectacular
gains along the Rhine throughout March, taking
some 100,000 prisoners. Though Field Marshal
Montgomery was organising an immense operation,
to cross the Rhine River with considerable
artillery and air support, on the 23rd of March,
with Patton’s forces already attempting a
crossing after building a pontoon bridge,
‘Old Blood and Guts’ phoned General Omar Bradley,
commander of the 12th army group and announced
that, quote, “You can tell the world, Third
Army made it before Monty.” Patton clearly
looked down on the cautious, methodical British
commander, whose operations he perceived as being
allocated too many Allied resources. Despite his
successes in Germany, Patton could be prone to
errors of judgement. For example, he sent a force
to liberate a prisoner camp near Hammelburg,
40 miles behind enemy lines, on the 26th of
March, having learned that his son-in-law,
was held captive there. This force was captured by
the Germans, while the camp was subsequently freed
a week later by other US forces, making
the operation a complete waste of men.
Annoyance at this setback turned to horror as
Patton and his men advanced further into Germany
and liberated the concentration camp at Ohrdurf in
April 1945. Even ‘Old Blood and Guts’, as tough as
he was, was shaken by what he witnessed there.
After a rapid advance through southern Germany,
against an exhausted Wehrmacht, Patton reached
the Czechoslovak border on the 4th of May. He
wanted to immediately push on to Prague before
the war ended and for the Allies to take part
in the capture of Berlin in order to limit the
Soviet sphere of influence in Central Europe,
however Eisenhower rejected this plan as it ran
counter to the terms of the Yalta conference,
where the Allied leaders had agreed that most of
Eastern Germany and Eastern Europe would become
Soviet spheres of influence after the war.
Nazi Germany surrendered to the Allies on the
7th of May 1945, bringing the Second World War to
an end in Europe, although VE day is celebrated on
the 8th of May. At that stage, Patton and the 3rd
Army had been in active combat since the 1st of
August 1944, a span of 281 days. Indeed, Patton’s
forces captured more land and prisoners than any
other Allied army in the European theatre. The
Allied invasion of Europe was thus the peak of
Patton’s military career, his finest campaign.
However, it would also be his last. Following
the German surrender, Patton returned home on the
7th of June 1945, for a brief period of leave,
during which time he spoke at huge gatherings
of admirers and took part in military parades.
He also lobbied for a command in the Pacific
theatre of war, where the US was still fighting
Japan. Instead, after returning to Europe,
he was appointed as military governor of the
German state of Bavaria, a political role that the
maverick Patton was not at all suited for. Once in
that position he attracted controversy with his
outspoken anti-Soviet and anti-Semitic remarks.
What most angered the US high command was his
tolerance of former Nazis in political posts
across local government in Bavaria. Furthermore,
Patton openly stated what most Allied commanders
already knew, but did not wish to say aloud,
that post-war Germany could not be properly
administered without the support of some
former Nazis, as there had been millions
of active members of the party. Many Allied
commanders probably partially empathised with his
inflammatory statements about continuing the war
and invading the Soviet Union as well, but they
were anathema to the Allied high command.
As the crisis over Patton’s statements continued,
he was relieved of his military governorship
by Eisenhower in late September. Then,
on the 7th of October 1945, he was relieved of the
command of the 3rd Army as well, causing Patton to
remark at the change of command that “All good
things must come to an end. The best thing that
has ever happened to me thus far, is the honour
and privilege, of having commanded the 3rd Army.”
Patton remained in Europe as commander of the 15th
Army. This was, though, largely an office job,
as the 15th Army was tasked with writing an
official historical account of the war in Europe.
In response to his demotion, Patton considered
retiring from the armed forces altogether.
However, he never returned home, as on the 9th
of December 1945, shortly before noon, Patton’s
car collided with a US army truck, causing him
severe injuries including a broken neck. Although
‘Old Blood and Guts’ lingered in hospital for 12
days, he eventually died on the 21st of December
1945 at the age of 60. He was buried, as he had
requested, alongside other soldiers of the 3rd
Army, near Luxembourg City in the Ardennes, the
site of one of his finest hours as a soldier.
George S. Patton was a giant of American military
history and is one of the most famous Allied
commanders of the Second World War, though he
was also one of the most controversial. Despite
his reputation as a tough, brute force soldier,
Patton was actually a military intellectual and
was well read on military history from his youth
onwards. For instance, he regularly contributed
to military journals on a range of topics. He also
saw where warfare was headed from early on in his
career. After serving in France during the First
World War, he concluded that armoured divisions of
tanks and other vehicles would be central to the
armies of the twentieth century. His deployment
of swift moving armoured divisions like this
made him an American version of Heinz Guderian,
the German commander who was responsible above
all others for the Blitzkrieg warfare deployed to
such effect in France and the Low Countries in the
summer of 1940 and against the Soviet Union in the
first months of the war with the Russians between
June and October 1941. Beyond his tactical skill,
Patton’s heroic style of leadership, placing
great emphasis on personal courage, led to the
perception of him as a great commander, one whom
the Germans genuinely feared. While he served for
four decades in the armed forces, his legacy was
ultimately carved out through three campaigns,
in North Africa between November 1942 and May
1943, in Sicily briefly in the summer of 1943,
and then in France, the Low Countries and
Germany between July 1944 and May 1945.
In each of these spheres he made his fellow
Allied commanders look like subpar generals,
winning striking victories and advancing at great
speed against the Germans and Italians where
others crept slowly forward. Patton’s character
was deeply paradoxical and controversial.
He was a highly religious man, but one who had a
dubious personal life and who often behaved in a
vulgar manner. His post-war correspondence while
governing Bavaria also leaves little doubt that
he was quite anti-Semitic. Nevertheless, his
unique character and command style has ensured
him an enduring place in American popular
culture. The 1970 film Patton about his life,
starring George C. Scott as ‘Old Blood and Guts’,
won seven academy awards and helped cement his
reputation as one of the most influential and
fascinating figures of the Second World War.
What do you think of George S Patton? Was he an
unstable warmonger who would have continued the
war by attacking the Soviet Union if he had
his own way, or was he a military genius who
surpassed all of America’s other generals,
including MacArthur and Eisenhower? Please
let us know in the comment section and in the
meantime, thank you very much for watching.